Guide to the Jerome Allen Papers MC 55
New York University Archives
Jerome Allen Papers
1867-1893
MC 55
New York University Archives
0.75 linear feet
This collection comprises a selection of Jerome Allen's published writings, including essays, books, and lectures, from the years 1867-1893.
Biography
Jerome Allen was born in Westminster, Vermont, on July 17, 1830. He began teaching at the age of seventeen and completed his first classes successfully, receiving high praise from the district selectman. Allen completed his undergraduate studies at Amherst College in 1851 and continued his education at Lenox College, receiving his Doctor of Philosophy degree in 1886. He acted as teacher and administrator at a number of educational institutions, including a time spent as the Superintendent of Schools in Monticello, Iowa. He accepted a professorship in the Natural Sciences at the State Normal School in Genesco, New York, and the Presidency of the State Normal School in St. Cloud, Minnesota. He was appointed Professor of Pedagogy at New York University in 1887 and named dean of the newly formed School of Pedagogy in 1890. Over the course of his career, Allen published extensively on the topics of pedagogy and the state of educational institutions. He also created a number of manuals on academic subjects and teaching. He died on May 26, 1894.
Arrangement
The files in this collection are arranged in a single series, chronologically by publication date.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the published books, essays, and lectures of Jerome Allen, written from 1867-1893.
Access Restrictions
Open for use without restrictions.
Allen, Jerome, 1830-1894; Education |x Study and Teaching |z United States.; Literature |x Study and teaching.
- Series I: Published Writings, 1867-1893
  - A Grammar and Analysis of the English Language, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Methods for Teachers. Part I, Grammar, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hand Book of Experimental Chemistry for Laboratory, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Short Studies in English, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Barnes' Picture Lessons in English or Short Stories Part I, 1886-1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Relation of Pedagogy to Christian Philosophy, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - To What Extent and How Can Manual Training be Introduced into Ungraded Schools?, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mind Studies for Young Teachers, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Relation of Pedagogy to the University, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Temperament In Education; Also Success in Teaching, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lectures on the History of Education, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lectures on the History of Education(Copy 2), 1891 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Training of Teachers in Scotland, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Outlines of Educational History, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Motive in Teaching, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Education of Teachers in the State of New York and a Brief History of Normal Schools, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)